<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Databricks on Zach Stagers</title>
    <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/tags/databricks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Databricks on Zach Stagers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/tags/databricks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Data and AI Summit 2022 Announcements</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/data-and-ai-summit-2022-announcements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/data-and-ai-summit-2022-announcements/</guid>
      <description>Data and AI Summit 2022 I&amp;rsquo;m absolutely buzzing after attending my first Data and AI Summit (DAAIS) in San Francisco last week (June 27th to 30th). Incredible key notes, fantastic venue and city, good people, and awesome after parties! Huge thank you to everyone at Databricks for putting the event together, and to Advancing Analytics for giving me the opportunity to attend.
As I sit on my flight home, mind racing over the events of the week, I wanted to be productive and write up some of the key announcements and share some initial thoughts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lakehouse Serving Options - 2022</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/lakehouse-serving-options-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/lakehouse-serving-options-2022/</guid>
      <description>I blogged previously on my thoughts about what makes a good lakehouse serving layer - the functionality and features to consider when trying to identify the right serving tool for you.
In this post I want to go a step further and do a direct comparison of some of the more obvious Azure based lakehouse serving tools - Synapse Serverless, Databricks SQL, and Synapse Dedicated. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to include Dedicated here, as although it defeats the purpose of the lakehouse paradigm, I&amp;rsquo;m still often asked whether it&amp;rsquo;s suitable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connect Azure Databricks to a DevOps repo in a different tenancy</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/connect-azure-databricks-to-a-devops-repo-in-a-different-tenancy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/connect-azure-databricks-to-a-devops-repo-in-a-different-tenancy/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re working with a large multi-tenancy organisation it&amp;rsquo;s possible the subscription your Databricks resource sits in is a different tenancy to the Azure DevOps hosting your repositories. This blog explains how to connect Databricks to a DevOps repository in that scenario.
When trying to connect to DevOps in a seperate tenancy, you&amp;rsquo;ll receive the message Unable to parse credentials from Azure Active Directory account. Ensure Azure Devops account is connected to AAD.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
