<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Lake on Zach Stagers</title>
    <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/tags/data-lake/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Lake on Zach Stagers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/tags/data-lake/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lakehouse Serving Options - 2022</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/lakehouse-serving-options-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/lakehouse-serving-options-2022/</guid>
      <description>I blogged previously on my thoughts about what makes a good lakehouse serving layer - the functionality and features to consider when trying to identify the right serving tool for you.
In this post I want to go a step further and do a direct comparison of some of the more obvious Azure based lakehouse serving tools - Synapse Serverless, Databricks SQL, and Synapse Dedicated. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to include Dedicated here, as although it defeats the purpose of the lakehouse paradigm, I&amp;rsquo;m still often asked whether it&amp;rsquo;s suitable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Makes a Good Lakehouse Serving Layer?</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/what-makes-a-good-lakehouse-serving-layer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/what-makes-a-good-lakehouse-serving-layer/</guid>
      <description>This post is a bit of an exploratory one, collecting some thoughts about features which combine to make a good data lakehouse serving layer, and the things to consider when choosing a resource to serve your data.
I do not intend for this post to act as a guide for choosing the right serving layer, but instead it&amp;rsquo;s an introduction to the subject and some things to watch out for as you identify which tool would be best for you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Azure Synapse Serverless Lake Access Patterns</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/azure-synapse-serverless-lake-access-patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/azure-synapse-serverless-lake-access-patterns/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with a client to build a large Data Lakehouse platform predominantly using Databricks as a processing engine and Synapse Serverless to serve the data out in a couple different ways.
This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;d properly used Synapse Serverless in anger, and to say I found the documentation around lake access confusing would be an understatement! Everything I needed to understand was spread over a few different articles, which I&amp;rsquo;ve linked to at the bottom of this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Azure Data Lake ACL Introduction</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/azure-data-lake-acl-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/azure-data-lake-acl-introduction/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to ACL&amp;rsquo;s Access Control Lists (ACLs) offer low-level control of access to the folders within your Azure Data Lake, whilst Role-Based Access Control (RBAC) offers high-level control to the entire lake.
RBAC vs ACL
The ACL permissions on offer are:
 Read - Grants read access to files and folders (i.e. able to see the contents). Write - Grants write access to files and folders. Execute - Grants&amp;hellip; execute.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
