<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Synapse on Zach Stagers</title>
    <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/tags/synapse/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Synapse on Zach Stagers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/tags/synapse/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lakehouse Serving Options - 2022</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/lakehouse-serving-options-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/lakehouse-serving-options-2022/</guid>
      <description>I blogged previously on my thoughts about what makes a good lakehouse serving layer - the functionality and features to consider when trying to identify the right serving tool for you.
In this post I want to go a step further and do a direct comparison of some of the more obvious Azure based lakehouse serving tools - Synapse Serverless, Databricks SQL, and Synapse Dedicated. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to include Dedicated here, as although it defeats the purpose of the lakehouse paradigm, I&amp;rsquo;m still often asked whether it&amp;rsquo;s suitable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Azure Synapse Serverless Lake Access Patterns</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/azure-synapse-serverless-lake-access-patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/azure-synapse-serverless-lake-access-patterns/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with a client to build a large Data Lakehouse platform predominantly using Databricks as a processing engine and Synapse Serverless to serve the data out in a couple different ways.
This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;d properly used Synapse Serverless in anger, and to say I found the documentation around lake access confusing would be an understatement! Everything I needed to understand was spread over a few different articles, which I&amp;rsquo;ve linked to at the bottom of this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQLBits 2022</title>
      <link>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/sqlbits-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.zachstagers.co.uk/p/sqlbits-2022/</guid>
      <description>This years arcade-themed SQLBits is taking place between March 8th and 12th. I&amp;rsquo;ve been to SQLBits a number of times, it&amp;rsquo;s always great fun and I come away having learned a ton!
However, this year is a little different from me, as I&amp;rsquo;ll be presenting for the first time! I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to it a lot, the last time I presented at a community event was on Azure Notebooks back in July 2018 (as seen in the banner image)!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
